Guide to the Charles Wilkes Papers, 1816-1876 RL.01383
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
The remainder of the correspondence of John Wilkes as well as that of some others pertains to mining and milling operations in the Charlotte area. In 1853 John went to North Carolina to be superintendent of the Capps mining operations and presumably to continue work begun by his brother Edmund earlier. John wrote about the condition of various mines, such as the Capps, McGinn, and Dunn mines; mining operations, such as pumping water out of the Capps mine shaft; his brief tenure as agent of the Capps Mining Company; problems with the Capps Company; and continual financial problems. By August, 1855, the Capps Mine was defunct. Charles Wilkes had been President of the St. Catherine's Mining Company. John also became involved in milling operations and sent back reports about the work, progress, and machinery repairs at the St. Catherine's Mills; stamp mills; flour and corn milling; and questions about Wilkes's ownership of St. Catherine's Mills. In 1858 John turned his attention to the Mecklenburg Flour Mills, which he purchased with William R. Myers. Other correspondence concerns a proposed St. Catherine Gold Mining Company, which would have been formed to sell a newly invented machine for reducing metallic ores.
There is considerably less bulk for the 1860s and 1870s than for earlier years, there being one box of material for each of these decades. Certain letters in 1860 begin to mention the possibility of secession. Throughout the Civil War period are references to various battles, ships, naval and army officers, and views on the war. On November 8, 1861, Charles Wilkes commanded that the British mail steamer Trent halt and be boarded. He then searched the vessel, arrested the Confederate commissioners James Mason and John Slidell, and removed them to the U.S. Ship San Jacinto. Wilkes's primary error was in searching a neutral vessel and seizing the agents on board, rather than bringing the ship into port. His actions became quite controversial both in the United States and in Europe. Although the British people were outraged by the events, a majority of Lincoln's cabinet applauded the act. The matter was finally resolved, though, when Secretary of State Seward released the prisoners, realizing that the alternative was war with England. Two letters in 1862, written by Michele Costi, a publicist living in Venice, address this affair. He wrote a strong defense of Wilkes's actions in the Trent affair. A copy of Costi's, In difesa del San Giacinto, is contained in the writings. There is no firsthand account by Wilkes of this affair in the collection.
In July and August, 1862, there is a series of letters from Secretary of the Navy Gideon Welles to Charles Wilkes, who was co landing the James River Flotilla at that time. Also in 1862 are various orders about ships, crews, and discharges, as well as letters concerning aspects of the U. S. Navy, such as health, medical care, surgeons, liquor, and deserters. Many of the letters in 1862 and 1863 comment on General George Brinton McClellan, particularly after his removal as commander-in-chief of the U. S. Army; the Wilkes family favored him. In late 1862 and early 1863 letters refer to the fact that Wilkes was passed over for promotion to rear admiral and to his reputation as an officer. His wife Mary had much correspondence attempting to secure the promotion. Wilkes was not promoted to rear admiral on the retired list until 1866. On June 1, 1863, he was detached from the West India Squadron and recalled home. Unfortunately his letters for this period at sea, 1861-1863, are not included in this collection. Only a handful of letters exist for 1864; two of them are from Wilkes to Gideon Welles concerning Wilkes's court-martial.
Family letters during the Civil War are concentrated mainly in 1862 and 1863, while Wilkes was at sea. His wife and two older daughters remained in Washington, D. C., and in their letters they discuss prominent citizens of the city, army generals, naval officers, and activities there. Many letters refer to business and financial matters.
At the conclusion of the Civil War, John Wilkes's letters from Charlotte to his father resume. John was at this time serving as the first president of the First National Bank of Charlotte and had resumed operations at the Mecklenburg Iron Works which he owned. His letters relate to business and economic conditions in North Carolina and the South during Reconstruction, making a start again after the Civil War, and business and financial matters. Wilkes was in a partnership that owned the Rock Island Manufacturing Company; letters refer to its financial problems. In about 1866, Charles Wilkes moved to Gaston County, North Carolina, where he had purchased the High Shoals Iron Works. He had a contract of sale, but no deed, so protracted legal battles ensued. The Iron Works continued to produce batches of pig iron and manufacture nails. Letters in the collection pertain to the Iron Works and its production. Only a few letters exist for 1868 and 1869.
The correspondence for the 1870s consists primarily of family letters, mostly written by John Wilkes to his father. Letters continue about the problems of the Rock Island Manufacturing Company, which had failed in about 1869. Other letters concern the Mecklenburg Iron Works, which was at one time called the Mecklenburg Foundry and Machine Shops, of which he was proprietor. He also referred to the continued question of ownership of the High Shoals Iron Works and the appropriation for the work of the Exploring Expedition in 1870. A few other letters were written by Mary and Edmund Wilkes, who went to live in Salt Lake City in 1871, but returned to New York later.
Other letters for the 1870s pertain to the Exploring Expedition. Charles Wilkes wrote to Lot M. Morrill about publishing the volumes of the work of the expedition. There are letters from Frederick D. Stuart, assistant to Wilkes, concerning funds to finish the publication of the Exploring Expedition volumes. It was difficult in the later years to obtain this funding from Congress.
The two clippings are a picture of Charles Wilkes and an article, 1862, concerning publication of the results of the Exploring Expedition.
The financial papers, 1830-1875, include such items as financial statements, Exploring Expedition statements, bills, receipts, cost estimate, and a bond.
In the legal papers, which span the years 1827-1865, are indentures, many of which are signed by Charles Wilkes and Richard B. Mason, among other parties. Also included are articles of association and other papers for the Jackson City Association, a signed approval by Secretary of the Navy Isaac Toucey of a summons to Wilkes for a trial, and undated plats. There are court documents, such as agreements, summons, a complaint, and a memorandum. Some of these items pertain to litigation concerning a Lynch vs. Wilkes family real estate dispute.
The miscellany consists of papers, 1825-1875. Exploring Expedition items include a memo in 1838 concerning the acting appointments as commanders of Charles Wilkes and William H. Hudson, magnetic measurements, and in 1858 a few items about revisions to various maps and publications of the expedition. Three depositions occur in this section in 1862 concerning fortifications at Drewry's Bluff. They are written by a deserter from the Confederate Navy, a former Confederate soldier, and a New York soldier who had been behind Confederate lines. Other Civil War papers in 1863 and 1864 relate to the court-martial of Wilkes.
The printed material spans the years 1849 to 1874. Included is a broadside that General John James Peck penned on September 20, 1864, entitled, Siege of Suffolk-Chancellorsville. The purpose of the paper was to debunk the idea that any significant portion of Longstreet's army was transferred to Chancellorsville. In the printed material also is Report on the High Shoals Property in Gaston County, North Carolina by F. Winter. This is a proof of the pamphlet written in 1873 concerning the geology of High Shoals. Other titles are Working the Gold Mines in New Granada, Prospectus of the American Review, and Map of the City of Zanesville.
While the writings cover the two years, 1862 to 1863, most of them are undated. Included is a copy in Italian of In difesa del San Giacinto, 1862, by Michele Costi. This was a defense of Wilkes's actions in the Trent affair. An English translation of this item was published as a pamphlet under the title, Memoir on the Trent Affair. A copy is housed in the Rare Book Room. Related items are The Surrender of Mason and Slidell written in Wilkes's hand and another article, both of which defend his actions in the Trent affair. Copies of Naval Reform and Abuses in the Navy, 1862, are also included. Two folders contain the sixteen-chapter manuscript Trip to the Far West by Charles Wilkes in 1863. The narrative is comprised of descriptions of the localities visited, including Pennsylvania, Illinois, Indiana, Milwaukee, the Mississippi River, St. Paul, Iowa (especially Dubuque), St. Louis, Cincinnati, Erie, New York--Buffalo and Niagara Falls, Maryland, Delaware, New Jersey, and New York City. Canal Trip in Peru is listed as being included with the manuscript but is not a part of this collection. Other undated writings describe various aspects of New York City, iron-clad vessels, New Jersey, and Baltimore.
The volumes, 1823-1847, include account books of Charles Wilkes, a notebook owned by Edmund Wilkes, and Notes related to Fejee [sic] Islands. There is an account book for the ship O'Cain, 1823, maintained while Wilkes was on a trip to ports in the South Atlantic on a sealing voyage. Wilkes was in command of the ship, which was fitted out by its owner, Mr. Winship. Other financial records of Charles Wilkes are in three Daybooks of Receipts and Expenses, 1828-1829, 1829-1832, and 1833-1835. Edmund Wilkes kept the notebook in 1847 while he was a student in Philadelphia. Evidently it was from a chemistry course. Charles Wilkes wrote Notes related to Fejee [sic] Islands from July 15 to August 7, 1840, while on the Exploring Expedition.
Two oversize items are in oversize storage: Map of the World shewing [sic] the Extent and Direction of the Wind and the Route To Be Followed in a Circumnavigation of the Globe by Charles Wilkes, 1856, and a broadside, including a plat of several lots of Charles Wilkes's land in Washington, D. C. for sale, May 12, 1874.
List of Selected Persons Whose Manuscripts Have Been Listed in the Autograph File of the Card Catalog
Abbot, Henry Larcon
Abert, John James [?]
Adrain, Robert
Agassiz, Jean Louis Rodolphe
Allen, Horatio
Allen, Philip
Almy, John Jay
Alvord, Benjamin (1813-1884) [?]
Arnold, Samuel Greene
Astor, William Backhouse
Bache, Alexander Dallas
Badger, George Edmund
Bailey, Jacob Whitman
Baird, Spencer Fullerton
Barnard, Daniel Dewey
Barney, John
Bartlett, John
Bartlett, John Russell (1805-1886)
Bayard, James Asheton 1799-1880)
Beaufort, Sir Francis
Beaulieu, A., Baron de (d. 1872)
Belcher, Sir Edward
Bertrand, Henri Gratien, Comte
Bigelow, Abraham [?]
Bille, Steen [?]
Bissell, Edward H.
Black, Jeremiah Sullivan
Blodget, Lorin
Bond, George Phillips
Bond, William Cranch
Bond, William Cranch and Son
Bonham, Sir Samuel George
Bowditch, Jonathan Ingersoll
Bowditch, Nathaniel, et al.
Brackenridge, William D
Bragg, Thomas
Branch, Lawrence O 'Bryan
Brinley, Francis
Campbell, George Washington [?]
Cantwell, Edward
Carpender, Edward W.
Carpenter, Stephen Haskins, et al.
Cassin, John
Cobb, Howell (1815-1868)
Coggeshall, George
Conover, Obediah Milton, et al.
Costi, Michele
Curtis, Edward (1801-1856)
Curtis, Moses Ashley
Cushing, Caleb
Dana, James Dwight (1813-1895)
Davis, Thomas Treadwell [?]
Devens, Charles
Disturnell, John
Dix, Dorothea Lynde
Dobbin, James Cochran
Dougal, William H.
Draper, Lyman Copeland
Draper, Lyman Copeland, et al.
Du Pont, Samuel Francis
Eastman, Seth
Emmons, George Foster
Endicott, Charles Moses, et al.
Ewbank, Thomas
Farragut, David Glasgow
Farwell, Leonard J., et al.
Fessenden, William Pitt
Fillmore, Millard
Fisher, Charles Frederick
Flugel, Johann Gottfried [?]
Foote, Andrew Hull
Force, Peter
Fraley, Frederick
Franklin, Jane (Griffin), Lady
French, B. B.
Genth, Frederick Augustus (1820-1893)
Gillespie, William Mitchell
Gillet, Ransom Hooker
Gilliss, James Melville
Glynn, James
Goldsborough, Louis Malesherbes
Gould, Augustus Addison
Graham, William Alexander
Gray, Asa
Grinnell, Joseph (1788-1885)
Guthrie, James
Gwin, William McKendree
Hale, John Parker
Halleck, Henry Wagner
Harris, Ira
Heath, James Ewell
Henderson, Archibald ([17xx?]-1859)
Henry, Joseph
Hogan, William
Horaford, Eben Norton
Hudson, William H.
Hughes, George Wurtz
Hull, Isaac
Humboldt, Alexander, Freiherr von
Humphreys, Andrew Atkinson
Ingraham, Duncan Nathaniel
Jackson, Charles Thomas [?]
Jarvis, Leonard
Jenkins, John Stilwell
Jewett, Charles Coffin
Johnson, Edwin Ferry
Johnson, Reverdy
Johnson, Walter R.
Johnston, John Taylor
Jones, Thomas Ap Catesby
Jones, Walter(1776-1861)
Judd, Gerrit Parmele
Kennedy, John Pendleton
Kennedy, Joseph Camp Griffith
King, Charles Bird
King, Daniel Putnam
Latrobe, Benjamin Henry (1806-1878)
Lawrence, Julia (Montaudevret)
Lawson, Thomas
Lea, Isaac
Lesley, J. Peter
Lieber, Francis
Locke, John (1792-1856)
Lovejoy, Owen
Lovering, Joseph
Lynch, William Francis [?]
McKeever, Isaac
Maclay, William Brown
Marchand, John Bonnett [?]
Marcy, Randolph Barnes
Mason, Charles
Mason, John Young
Mason, Richard Barnes
Maury, Matthew Fontaine [?]
Meehan, John Silva
Meigs, Montgomery Cunningham
Memminger, Christopher Gustavus
Meredith, William Morris
Miller, Jacob Welsh
Miller, William Starr
Mills, Robert (1781-1855) [?]
Morell, George Webb
Morton, Samuel George
Neal, John
Nelson, John (1794-1860)
Ogden, Francis Barber
Ogden, Peter Skene
Olmsted, Denison
Osborne, James W.
Parker, Amasa Junins (1807-1890)
Peale, Titian Ramsay
Pearce, James Alfred
Peck, John James
Percival, John [?]
Perry, Matthew Calbraith
Pickering, Charles
Porter, William David (1809-1864) et al.
Preston, William Ballard
Preston, William Campbell
Putnam, G. P. and Co.
Putnam, George Palmer (1814-1872)
Renwick, Edward Sabine
Renwick, Henry Brevoort
Renwick, James (1792-1863)
Renwick, James (1818-1895)
Rhees, William Jones
Ringgold, Cadwalader
Roberts, Solomon White
Rogers, William Barton
Ropes, Joseph, et al.
Rutherfurd, Lewis Morris [?]
Sabine, Sir Edward
Schieffelin, Samuel Bradhurst [?]
Schmidt, Charles
Scott, Gustavus H.
Seward, William Henry
Shufeldt, Robert Wilson (1822-1895)
Silliman, Benjamin (1779-1864)
Smith, Joseph (1790-1877)
Snow, William Parker
Somerville, Mary
Squier, Ephraim George
Steiner, Lewis Henry
Stuart, Alexander Hugh Holmes
Sullivant, William Starling
Tappan, Benjamin (1773-1857)
Thompson, David (1798-1871)
Thompson, James
Thompson, Smith
Thurston, Samuel Royal
Tompkins, Daniel D.
Torrey, John
Totten, George Muirson
Totten, Joseph Gilbert
Toucey, Isaac
Tuckerman, Edward
Twining, Alexander Catlin [?]
Upshur, Abel Parker
Vattemare, Alexandre (see Vattemare, Nicolas Marie Alexandre)
Vattemare, Nicolas Marie Alexandre
Walbridge, Hiram
Waldo, Loren Pinckney
Walker, Robert John
Warren, Gouverneur Kemble
Webb, James Watson
Welles, Gideon
Welles, Mary Jane (Hale)
Whitney, Asa (1797-1872)
Wilkes, Charles (1798-1877)
Wilkes, John(1827-1908)
Willard, Sidney [?]
Willis, Nathaniel Parker
Winslow, Warren
Winter, F.
Winthrop, Robert Charles
Worcester, Joseph Emerson
Worth, William Scott [?]
Wright, Richard
Wyman, Robert Harris
Selective Index of References to Persons, Places, and Subjects
Abbot, Henry Larcon [?] 1863 June 9; 1863 June 17.
Abbot, Joel 1852 Nov. 27
Abbot, Trevett [?] 1863 Jan. 18
Abernathy, George 1849 Mar. 2
Abert, John James 1843 Mar. 26
Adams, John Quincy 1825 Mar. 28; 1828 Nov. 14; 1845 [?] Feb. 5; 1848 Mar. 15.
Adams, Louisa Catherine (Johnson), 1825 Mar. 22; 1825 Apr. 9; 1825 Aug. 9; 1828 Nov. 14; 1849 Apr. 12; 1849 Apr. 20.
Adams family. New York 1848 Mar. 22
Agassiz, Jean Louis Rudolphe, 1849 Apr. 18; 1849 May 12; 1849 June 7; 1850 Apr. 10; 1850 Apr. 12; 1850 July 20; 1850 Sept. 24; 1850 Oct. 11; 1850 Dec. 3; 1850 Dec. 14; 1852 Nov. 12 (on letter of Nov. 11); 1855 June 24; 1857 Apr. 9; 1857 May 26; 1857 June 8; 1857 Nov. 28; 1859 July 19
Agate, Alfred T. 1844 May 15
Agriculture. California 1849 Mar. 2
Agriculture. Minnesota Writings: Trip to the Far West
Agriculture. North Carolina 1856 May 31
Aiken, William 1851 Feb. 5; 1852 May 26.
Airy, Sir George Biddell Letter to: 1836, Sept. 3
Alcohol and Military Personnel 1862 July 26; 1862 Aug. 26.
Alcoholism and Crime. North Carolina, 1874 July 27
Alden, James [?] 1870 Sept. 29
Alexander, John Henry 1849 Apr. 28
Algae 1850 Nov. 6; 1851 Feb. 7[?]; 1851 Feb. 8.
Algeria. Algiers. Pratique 1830 Sept. 3; 1830 Sept. 12; 1830 Oct. 4.
Algeria. Algiers. Quarantine, 1830[?] Sept. 3
Algeria. Algiers. Steamboats, 1830 Aug. 19
Algeria. Dey 1830[?] Sept. 3
Algeria. French Abroad 1830 Oct. 4
Algeria. History. French Expidition, 1830 1830[?] Sept. 3
Algeria. Muslims 1830[?] Sept. 3
Alexander, Abraham 1849 May 17
Allen, Charles M. Letter to: 1862[?] Sept. 30
Allison, William Boyd 1874 May 1
Almy, John Jay[?] 1870 Aug. 13
Amalgamation 1848 Aug. 29; 1854 Mar. 18; 1854 Mar. 29.
American Association for the Advancement of Science 1852 Nov. 25
American Geographical Society, 1874 Dec. 28
Americans Abroad. Australia 1839 Dec. 3
Americans Abroad. Brazil 1838 Nov. 25
Americans Abroad. France 1830 Dec. 21
Americans Abroad. Hong Kong 1850 June 23; 1850 Oct. 2; 1850 Dec. 3; 1851 Mar. 31.
Americans Abroad. Macao 1850 Sept. 2
Anderson, Henry James 1834 Dec. 31
Annual Record of Science and Industry Printed Material: 1874
Antarctic Regions. Discovery and Exploration 1828 Mar. 18; 1829 Jan. 2; 1829 Jan. 11; 1829 May 7; 1836 July 18-1837 June 10 (scattered); 1837 Dec.-1841 (Letters of Charles Wilkes),; 1842 Feb. 20; 1842 Aug. 28; 1843 Aug. 4; 1843 Aug. 21; 1844 Jan. 21; 1844[?]; 1845 Feb. 1; 1845 Feb. 9; 1848 Mar. 13
Anthony, Henry Bowen 1863 Jan. 27
Arabs 1830[?] Sept. 3
Arnold, Samuel Greene 1862 Nov. 30; 1863 Jan. 27; 1863 Jan. 28; 1863 Feb. 12; 1863 Feb. 25; 1863 Mar.[?].
Art. Italy. Galleries and Museums 1830 Nov. 9
Aspinwall, William Henry 1849 July 27; 1853 Oct. 17.
Astor, John Jacob (1763-1848), 1836 Feb. 19
Astronomy. Astronomical Instruments, 1833[?]; 1836 July 18; 1836 Sept. 7; 1836 Oct. 9; 1836 Oct. 12; 1837 Jan. 30 (2); 1837 Sept. 2; 1837 Nov. 17 (enclosed with letter of Nov. 30); 1837 Dec. 7; 1838 Jan. 8; 1838 Apr. 4; 1838 Apr. 7; 1838 June 4.
Astronomy. Observations 1838 Jan. 24; 1838 Dec. 29.
Atkinson, Thomas 1857 May 24
Aulick, John H.[?] 1837 Dec. 31; 1838 June 5; 1841 Mar. 14; 1841 Nov. 22; 1841 Nov. 27; 1851 Sept. 15[?]; 1851 Dec. 8.
Australia. Americans in 1839 Dec. 3
Australia. English in 1839 Dec. 3
Australia. Governors 1839 Dec. 2; 1839 Dec. 3.
Australia. Observatories 1839 Dec. 10
Australia. Prisoners 1839 Dec. 10
Australia. Social Life and Customs, 1939 Dec. 3
Australia. Sydney. Balls (Parties), 1840[?] Mar.
Australia. Sydney. Description and Travel 1839 Dec. 2; 1839 Dec. 3.
Babcock, Orville Elias 1876 Feb. 21
Bache, Alexander Dallas 1844 May; 1844 July 20; 1844 July 24; 1844 July 30; 1846 Jan. 25; 1846 Aug. 6; 1851 May 1; 1852 Nov. 19; 1859 Aug. 20.
Bailey, Jacob Whitman 1857 Jan. 31; 1857 July 6; 1857 July 8; 1857 July 13; 1860 Jan. 3.
Bailey, Theodorus [?] 1863 Jan. 12; 1863 Jan 13.
Bachman, John 1850 July 20
Baird, Spencer Fullerton 1857 June 8; 1857 June 10; 1857 Dec. 29; Printed Material: 1874.
Balearic Islands. Port Mahon, 1830 Aug. 19; 1830 Aug. 25.
Balearic Islands. Port Mahon. Maps, 1830 Aug. 19
Balls (Parties). Australia. Sydney 1840[?] Mar.
Balls (Parties). Brazil 1838 Dec. 18
Balls (Parties). Chile 1839 June 12
Balls (Parties). District of Columbia, 1849 Mar. 18[?]
Balls (Parties). France 1831 Jan. 13
Balls (Parties). Macao 1851 Apr. 19 (with letter of Mar. 31)
Balls (Parties). Philippine Islands. Manila 1851 Jan. 27
Bancroft, George 1846 Feb. 17
Banks, Nathaniel Prentiss 1862 Nov. 14; 1862 Dec. 5.
Banks and Banking. District of Columbia, 1870 July 15
Banks and Banking. Massachusetts 1850 Apr. 19
Banks and Banking. North Carolina 1870 Aug. 3
Banks and Banking. North Carolina. Charlotte 1865 May 20; 1865 June 20; 1866 Dec. 14.
Baptism 1827 Mar. 12; 1845 Jan. 13.
Barnard, Daniel Dewey 1850 Nov. 23 (with letter of Oct. 31)
Barnard, Frederick Augustus Porter [?], 1857 Nov. 12; 1863 June 9.
Barney, John Letter to: 1842 Nov. 29 (in letter of May 3 1852)
Barringer, Daniel Moreau [?], 1849 Nov. 26; 1859 July 3; 1870 Apr. 11.
Barringer, Rufus 1870 July 27
Barringer, Rufus [?] 1875 Jan. 3; 1875 May 16; 1875 Aug. 1.
Bartlett, John Russell (1805-1886), Letter to: Note on letter of 1849 Apr. 16; 1849 Feb. 12; 1849 Feb. 13; 1849 Feb. 15; 1849 Feb 17; 1850 Aug. 6.
Batteries 1862 Aug. 9
Bay State Mills 1850 Oct. 22
Beaumont, Andrew 1847 Mar. 8
Bedouins 1830 Sept. 12
Belcher, Sir Edward 1840 June 22
Benham, Henry Washington 1838 Feb. 3
Benton, Thomas Hart (1782-1858)[?], 1849 May 15
Berkeley, Miles Joseph 1949 Oct. 9
Bernard, Simon [?] 1825 Aug. 12; 1825 Aug. 16.
Bible. Criticism, Interpretation, Etc., 1850 Apr. 12
Biddle, James (1783-1848) 1830 Nov. 9; 1837 Dec. 31.
Bigelow, Jacob 1857 May 26
Biggs, Asa 1857 May 24
Bissell, Edward H. 1835 Mar. 9; Late 1849 (a few); 1849 Jan. 20; 1849 Jan. 21; 1849 Feb. 10 (2); 1849 Feb. 13 (2); 1849 Mar. 1; 1849 Mar. 5; 1849 Mar. 6; 1849 Mar. 10; 1849 Mar. 14; 1849 Mar. 22; 1849 Mar. 24; 1849 Mar. 25; 1849 Mar. 31; 1849 Apr. 20; 1849 May 30; 1849 June
Black, Jeremiah Sullivan Letter to: 1857 June 30
Blast Furnaces 1846, Oct. 3
Bloodletting 1837 Dec. 6
Blunt, Edmund 1843 Apr. 14
Blunt, George William 1837 Jan. 30 (2); 1837 June 10; 1838 Jan. 8; 1838 June 4; 1838 June 11; 1843 Mar. 5; 1843 Mar. 13; 1843 Mar. 18; 1843 Apr. 14.
Bolivar, Simon 1822 Aug. 14; 1825 Nov. 25.
Bonaparte, Jerome Napoleon Letter to: 1852 May 3 (in letter of same date)
Bond, William Cranch 1838 July 19; 1859 Feb. 4.
Bonham, Sir Samuel George 1851 Mar. 31; 1859 June 6; 1859 June 16.
Boomerangs 1852 Jan. 31
Borie, Adolph Edward 1870 Dec. 9
Boyle John Letter to: 1836 July 18
Boyle John[?] 1837[?] June 25; 1837 Dec. 2; 1837 Dec. 29; 1838 Jan. 7.
Brackenridge, William D. 1849 May 5; 1849 May 6; 1849 May 12; 1849 May 17; 1849 May 21; 1849 June 7; 1849 June 15; 1849 June 22; 1849 June 29; 1849 July 31; 1849 Aug. 10; 1849 Aug. 14; 1849 Sept. 12; 1849 Oct. 24; 1849 Oct. 26; 1850 Jan. 15; 1850 Apr. 11; 1850 May 24; 1850 June 1
Bradish, Luther 1849 Apr. 28 (enclosed with letter of same date)
Bradley, Charles William 1850 Dec. 29
Bradley, Joseph P. 1870 Sept.[?]; 1870 Nov. 8; 1874 Oct. 25.
Bradley, Joseph P. [?] 1870 Dec. 19; 1870 Dec. 21; 1870 Dec. 26; 1874 June 10; 1874 June 23.
Bragg, Braxton 1857 May 24
Branch, John Letter to: 1829 May 7; 1831 Jan. 30; 1831 Apr. 26.
Branch, Lawrence O'Bryan 1858 July 25; 1859 July 3.
Brazil. Americans in 1838 Nov. 25
Brazil. Balls (Parties) 1838 Dec. 18
Brazil. English in 1838 Dec. 18
Brazil. Rio de Janeiro. Description and Travel 1822 Feb. 7; 1850 Mar. 14.
Brazil. Social Life and Customs 1838 Nov. 25
Breckinridge, John Cabell 1854 Mar. 30
Breese, Samuel L. [?] 1853 Aug. 1
Brent, Daniel Letter to: 1836 Nov. 20
Brenton, John (b. 1782) 1830 July 19
Breveport, James Carson [?], 1847 Feb. 7; 1847 Mar. 11; 1847 Mar. 12.
Bridgers, Robert Rufus 1866 Dec. 14; 1873 Dec. 1; 1873 Dec. 26; 1874 Jan. 12; 1874 Jan. 21; 1874 Mar. 4; 1874 Mar. 21; 1874 Mar. 31; 1874 Apr. 7; 1874 Apr. 16; 1874 Apr. 22 (2); 1874 Nov. 8.
Bridgers, Robert Rufus [?] 1867 Sept. 11; 1867 Oct. 16; 1867 Oct. 24; 1867 Dec. 29; 1870 Dec. 26.